<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The deyenge creature</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1514</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19600</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6035</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S122481</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99857607</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99857607</idno>
            <idno type="VID">23368</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19600)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 23368)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 33:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The deyenge creature</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p. : ill. (woodcuts)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Fletestrete at the sygne of ye sone by [Robert Copland? for] Wynkyn de Worde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Enprynted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno d[omi]ni. M.CCCCC.xiiii. [1514]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; actual printer's name conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁶ C⁴.</note>
                  <note>This state has Robert Copland's device on C4v.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Death --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:23368:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:23368:1"/>
            <p>¶The deyenge creature.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut representing a man in bed looking up toward Jesus Christ on the cross surrounded by people and animals, and with a devil or demon below the bed;</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:23368:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut representing a man in bed looking up toward Jesus Christ on the cross surrounded by angels and saints with halos, and with six devils or demons below the bed; a smaller figure or soul is being taken from the man's head by four winged figures</figDesc>
                  <p>INRI</p>
                  <p>Confuſi ſum</p>
                  <p>Heu infame</p>
                  <p>Furore conſumor</p>
                  <p>Animim amiſimus</p>
                  <p>Spes nobis nulla</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:23368:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Las that euer I ſynned in my lyfe to me is come this daye the dredfull tydynges that euer I herde / here hath ben with, me a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geaunt of armes whoſe name is crewelte frome the kynge of all kynges / lorde of all lordes / and Iuge of al Iuges lyenge on me his mace of his offyce ſayenge vnto me I areſt you &amp; warne you to make you redy and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye fayle not to be redy euery houre whan ye be called on / ye ſhall not wete whan. And cal ſadly to your remembraunce your olde and longe conty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nued offences / the goodnes of god how largely he hath departed with you the gyftes of nature / the gyftes of fortune &amp; the gyftes of grace / &amp; how he hath departed with you largely and ordeyned you at your baptim thre ſad borowes that ye ſholde ſaufely and ſurely be kepte in your tender aege as well frome vyces as fro bodyly pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryll &amp; ordeyned you a good aungell to kepe you and to counſeyl you yf ye haue be cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeylled by hym bethynke you. And whan ye come to the yere of dyſcrecyon he or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deyned you thre ſad counſeyllers / reaſon / drede / and conſcyence yf ye haue be rewled by theyr counſeyll call that to your remembraunce. He ordeyned you alſo .v. wyttes / ſeruauntes that ye ſholde be mayſter of &amp; rule them after your dyſcrecyon / that is to ſaye your felyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge / your ſyght / your herynge / your ſpeche / and your taſt How haue ye rewled theſe that be vnder youre obeyſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce me thynketh ye haue moche thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge to anſwere for for the Iuge that ſhall ſytte vpon you he wyll not be percyall nor he wyll not be corrupte with good but he wyll mynyſter to you Iuſtyce &amp; equyte certay<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly as well as this There were certayne thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges he forbad you and the thynges ye ſholde flee in ony wyſe / that is to were
<pb facs="tcp:23368:3"/> the ſeuen deedly ſynnes / and al thynges that ſholde pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uoke moue or ſtere you therto he badde you flee / haue ye do ſoo / haue ye kepte his commaundementes .x. And yet that is but lytell thynge.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶The lamentacyon of the dyenge creature.</head>
               <p>ALas alas excuſe me I can not / and whome I myght deſyre to ſpeke for me I wote not / the daye and tyme is ſo dredful / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iuge is ſo ryghtfull myn enmyes be cruell my kyn my neyghbours my frendes my ſeruauntes be not fauourable to me / and alſo I wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te well they ſhall not be herde there.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶The complaynt of the dyenge. creature to the good aungell.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> My good aungell to whome our lorde toke me to kepe where be ye now me thynketh ye ſholde be here now and anſwere for me for the drede of deth dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroubleth me ſo that I can not anſwere for my ſelfe he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re is my bad aungell redy and is one of my chefe accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers with legyons of fendes with hym and I haue no creature to anſwere for me / alas it is an heuy caas.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶The anſwere of the good aungell to the dyenge creature.</head>
               <p>S to your badde dedes I was neuer conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge. I ſawe your natural inclynacyon more dyſpoſed to be rewled by your bad aungell than by me how be it ye can not excuſe you but whan ye were pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed
<pb facs="tcp:23368:3"/> to de ony thynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was contrary to to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dementes of god I fayled not to remembre you that it was not wel and counſeylled you to flee the places of pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryll and the company that ſholde ſtere or moue you ther to can ye ſaye nay hereto / how can ye thynke that I cou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de anſwere for you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶The complaynt of the dyenge creature to reaſon drede and conſcyence.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Ye reaſon drede and conſcye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ye were aſſygned to be of my counſeyll now come I requyre you &amp; helpe me to anſwere for me for my defautes be ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and ſo abhomynable in the ſyght of hym that ſhall be my Iuge and my accuſers be ſo many &amp; ſo vnfrendly that they leue not one defaute behynde. Now come I requyre you &amp; helpe to anſwere for me for it was neuer ſo grete nede. The fere and the drede that I am in dyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>troubleth me ſo that one worde I can not ſpeke for my ſelfe. Alas that euer I ſawe this daye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶The anſwere of reaſon.</head>
               <p>BE ye remembred that our lorde ordeyned you a good aungel and a badde aungell / &amp; he ordeyned you reaſon &amp; dyſcrecyon to knowe the good frome the yll &amp; he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded you to do good &amp; leue the euyll / he put you in free choyſe whether ye wolde do well or euyl ye ought to call to your remembraunce how well god hath done for you &amp; helped you in euery daunger &amp; pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryll he wolde haue ben loued dred &amp; ſerued accordynge to the manyfolde graces and kyndeneſſes that he hath ſhewed vnto you how to anſwere for you I wote not lothe I am to accuſe you / and excuſe you I can not.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:23368:4"/>
               <head>¶The complaynt of the dyenge creature to drede ſaynge thus.</head>
               <p>A Drede where be ye is there no helpe and ſocour with you to ſpeke for me whan I ſhall come to my Iugement.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶The anſwere of drede.</head>
               <p>NO certaynly for whan ye where ſet in pleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce &amp; delectacyon of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde reaſon put put in your mynde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye dyde not wel / and I drede was w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you at all tymes and in euery place and fayled not to ſpeke vnto you and to put you in mynde of the ſame of this worlde and drede of dampnacyon and of the peryll that wolde folowe as well here as elles where reherſynge vnto you the punyſſhementes that our lorde ordeyned for ſynne ſaynge vnto you. Se ye not how gracyouſly our lorde hath called you frome ſynne &amp; wretchednes yf ye wolde vnderſtande it / how hath he longe kepte you in worſhyp eſtate and in proſperyte and coude not knowe the goodnes of god / how hath he chaſtyſed you and how ofte by loſſe of your chyldren / loſſe of your kyn and frendes / loſſe of youre goodes and loſſe of all tho thynges that ye coude not be pleaſed with and ſet you in the indygnacyon of the grete hygh and myghty prynce and helpe you out of the daungers and perylles that ye haue ben in at all tymes / and yet haue ye not loued hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dred hym and ſerued hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that in all theſe perylles hath preſerued and kepte you and hath ben ſo gracyous and good lorde to you who ſholde ſpeke for you. I / nay cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶The complaynt of the dyenge creature to conſcyence ſaynge thus.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:23368:4"/>
               <p>ALas conſcyence is there no helpe with you I haue herde ſaye longe ago the worlde was to curſte / but I wolde hope that conſcyence wolde haue compaſſyon of my dyſtreſſe and moche the more that I am frendles.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶The anſwere of conſcyence to the dyenge creature.</head>
               <p>I Am ſory to accuſe you and excuſe you I can not for conſcyence and drede haue ben but ſeldome frome you and called vpon you in euery tyme &amp; place of peryll &amp; bad you flee y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> occaſyons of ſynne ye myght haue fled at that tyme and wolde not / now ye wolde fleedeth and can not / we ſholde ſpeke for you &amp; dare not &amp; though we wolde it auayleth not ye muſt ſorowfully and mekely ſuffre y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Iugeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes that ye haue deſerued</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶The complaynt of the dyenge creature, to the fyue wyttes.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Ye fyue that were ordeyned to be my ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes &amp; vnder myn obeyſaunce &amp; to haue be rewled at all tymes as I wolde haue you / is there no good worde that ye may aforde to ſaye for me and recorde my deme<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge to you &amp; reporte of me how I haue rewled and gouerned you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were take me to kepe rewle &amp; gouerne me thynketh ye ſholde ſaye for me now / who myght ſo well ſaye for me as ye fyue / ye haue ben with me con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynually euer ſyth that I was borne nyght and daye and neuer at no tyme from me thynketh of your kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deneſſe ye ſholde haue compaſſyon vpon me and ſaye the beſt that ye coude ſaye for me. I haue ben frendely to you and brought you in euery place of pleaſaunce and ſpeke to fayth and hope for me that they wolde
<pb facs="tcp:23368:5"/> charytably doo my meſſage vnto the mooſt gloryous prynce that euer was is or ſhalbe</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶The anſwere of the fyue wyttes.</head>
               <p>CErtaynly we meruayle that ye wolde deſyre vs to ſpeke for you vnderſtandy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g theſe worſhip full people haue denyed and refuſed to ſpeke for you your good aungell reaſon drede and conſcyence / how ſholde we be herde or what credence wyl be gyuen vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to vs that haue ben your ſaruauntes and vnder your obeyſaunce and no thynge at all tymes but as ye ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded vs to do call to your reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce how ye haue rewled vs ryue / ſyght / herynge / felynge and thought ye haue at all tymes brought vs in places of pleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; dyſporte / &amp; thoughe it were dyſporte and pleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / for the tyme it is now ſorowe wepynge and waylynge for your ſake y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we can not excuſe you nor no thynge ſaye for you that myght be to your wele or to your ele for we haue ben preuy &amp; partyners to al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath ben myſdone in ony wyſe and in euery place and your offentes in euery thynge is in your defaute for and ye hadde ſadly ruled vs and lyke a ſouerayne ye ſholde haue reſtrayned in vs euery vyce for we ſholde haue be ruled by you in euery thynge / &amp; other wyſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye wolde haue vs do we wold not do therfor of ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſite your defautes muſt be layd vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you for we ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue do as ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes ſhold do &amp; obeyed you in euery thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge &amp; dyſobeyed you in no thynge / wherfore of ryght y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peryll muſt be yours what credence wyll ye gyue to vs tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yf we ſhold ſay well of you the people wolde ſay, that we were fals diſſymulours &amp; fauourers of ſynne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:23368:5"/>
               <head>¶The lamentacyon of the dyenge creature.</head>
               <p>ALas there is no creature that I can complayn me to but vtterly refuſeth to ſaye ony thynge that myght be to my comforte.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>playnt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dyenge creature to fayth &amp; hope.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Holy fayth &amp; hope in you is all my truſte for how greuouſly and how myſcheuouſly y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer I offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded god you dyſpleaſed I neuer. I haue alway byleued as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chryche of cryſtendome hath taught me and ſpecy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally is of the mooſt holy incarnacyon I was neuer in thought. I haue byleued in the bleſſyd and mooſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryous trynyte fader ſone and holy gooſt I haue byleued that the ſeconde perſone of the trynyte deſcended in to the boſom of the mooſt gloryous and pure chaſt meke vyrgyn that euer was is or ſhall be and medled his very godhede with her pure chaſt vyrgynyte &amp; maydenheed and in her boſom was parfytly very god and man con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyued by the grete myſtery of the holy gooſt without knowlege or company of ony erthly ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and ſhe a pure chaſt vyrgyn flowrynge in vyrgynyte and by herynge of the holy archaungell Gabryell whiche brought vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came to man kynde. Now holy Fayth take with you hope &amp; ye twayne of your perfyte charyte be my aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates in the hyghe courte / and refuſe me not nor dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayne me not for myne horryble and abhominable ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes that I haue done / whiche aſked vengeaunce in this worlde / and dampnacyon eternall without the mercyes of hym whiche is almyghty / what meane
<pb facs="tcp:23368:6"/> myght I haue therto. I praye you counſeyll me for ye knowe well that my reaſon neuer dyſcorded with the fayth / and as to you Hope I hope all wayes that ye wyl ſaye for me that I haue alwayes hoped to the mercyes of god almyghty and that I ſholde be one of the chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of ſaluacyon and one of tho that ſholde be rede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the precyous and bytter paynfull paſſyon as other ſynners haue be and certaynly other plee nor re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyſtence I can not make. But and ye twayne wolde be a meane for me to that mooſt gloryous and pure chaſte vyrgyne that choſen was by one aſſent of all the hole gloryous trynyte to doo the mooſt gloryous and worſhypfull acte that euer was done for her chaſtyte her pure vyrgynyte her mekeneſſe her vertue and her conſtaunce was cauſe that ſhe was choſen by all the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le gloryous trynyte to be doughter mother and ſpouſe to the mooſt gloryous trynyte and that the ſholde bere hym that ſholde redeme all mankynde from dampna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon who may ſoo well be aduocatryſe to the fader the ſone and the holy gooſt as ſhe and ye wyll be meane to her ſone for me I hope ſhe wyll not refuſe me / for I vnderſtande and knowe well that ſhe hath holpe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a ſynner that hath ryght greuouſly offended and in the holy pſalme that was made bytwene her and her coſyn ſaynt Elyzabeth it was ſayd that all generacy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons ſholde blyſſe her. I hope at the begynnynge of the worlde oure lorde put not me out of his nombre of tho that ſholde blyſſe his mooſt holy moder and recorde her mercy pyte and grace that ſhe ſhewed to ſynners whan they haue none other ſocour ne helpe. She is moder of orphans / and ſhe is conſolacyon of theym that ben dyſſolate ſhe is guyde to all that be out of the waye
<pb facs="tcp:23368:6"/> to ſet theym in the ryght waye. I am an orphan I am dyſſolate. I am out of the waye I wote not where to crye and call after ſocoure and helpe but onely to her that bare our redemptour who may ſo well be meane to the ſone as the moder. And ye twayne Fayth and Hope wolde be meane to the moder of mercy for me. Now gracyous Fayth and Hope doo your parte and dyſdayne not my requeſt thoughe I deſyre you to this occupacyon / ſo, and ye twayne wolde denye to ſaye for me I thynke I ſhal fall in dyſpayre for on whome to call after ſocour I wote not / and to put my ſelfe in prees as a poore naked beeſt vnclothed of vertue and repleted with vyces naked of grace and in myn owne defaute and to come to the preſence of the kynge of all kynges and vnpouruayed of all thynges that wolde accorde with his moſte ryall and Imperyall eſtate I dare not take it vpon me I ſholde be in ſuche drede and fere I ſholde not con ne dare not ſpeke for my ſelfe for I haue prayed my good aungell to ſpeke for me and he hath denyed it. I haue called vpon Reaſon Drede and Conſcyens and they haue anſwered me full heuyly that they be lothe to accuſe me and exſcuſe me they can not / and alledgeth many a grete reſonable cauſe why y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I can not ſay nay to. I haue called vpon my ſeruaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes whiche were take me to rewle and gouerne as I wolde anſwere for theym / and they anſwere me ryght ſorowfully and ſay yf they ſholde ſay ony good worde for me they ſholde not ſaye trouth of me and caſteth to me that peryll that no body wolde geue credence vnto theym yf they wolde ſaye well on me but call theym. flaterers fals dyſſymulours and flaterers of ſynne. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las alas I haue heuyly dyſpended my longe lyfe that
<pb facs="tcp:23368:7"/> in all this longe tyme I haue not purchaſed me one frende to ſpeke for me. Had our lorde of his mooſt am<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple grace ordeyned me immedyatly after my cryſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to haue dyed forth with I myght ſaye I had be borne in a gracyous houre. But wolde it pleaſe your goodnes to ſpeke for me and vnderſtande whether I ſhall haue hardynes to make a byll to the bleſſyd lady and mooſt holy vyrgyn that euer was and ſhe that dyſdayneth not nor denyeth not ſynfull ſynners whan they call after grace. Notwithſtandynge her chaſtyte and her pure vyrgynyte excelleth all other vyrgyns.</p>
               <p>Now good go your waye &amp; lette me wete how I ſhall ſpede for all this tyme I lyue in ſuche drede and fere y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> me were better dye anone than lyue ony lenger in the drede that I am in. And alſo I haue ſo grete drede and fere of the ryghtwyſnes of almyghty god that I am almooſt deed for fere. for reaſon drede and conſcyence ſayd to me full ſhortly that the hyghe Iuge ſholde not be percyall nor he wolde not be corrupte with good but he wyll mynyſter to me Iuſtyce certaynly but and he atteyneth to mynyſter to me Iuſtyce without fauour I wyll appele to his mercyes certaynly for other reme<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy is there none parde. Origene our bleſſyd lady helpe Thyophyle &amp; ſyr Emery how ſholde they haue done ne the moder of mercy had ben and many another ſynner that her grace hath holpe. She is quene of heuen lady of the worlde and empreſſe of hell / and ſaynge to her ſone cryſte Ieſu hath dyed and ſuffred ſo tourmentous a deth and in her owne ſyght to her grete ſocour and mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derly compaſſyon I hope ſhe wolde be lothe that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eke precyous paſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſholde be loſte in ony creature that her blyſſed ſone ſuffred ſo paciently.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:23368:7"/>
               <head>¶The anſwere of fayth &amp; hope to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dyenge creature.</head>
               <p>HAue ye none acqueyntaunce with our brother Charyte we meruayle that ye haue not ſpoken of hym in all this tyme / for and ye were Joyned with vs twayne your meſſage ſholde be the more accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly herde manyfolde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶The lamentable complaynt of the dyenge creature to fayth hope and charyte.</head>
               <p>CErtaynly I haue but lytell deled with hym I was neuer conuerſaunt with hym &amp; that me repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth now for I fele by you twayne that he may do moche in the hygh courte I haue more deled with ven<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geaunce than I haue with charyte / for I wolde haue ben auenged vpon euery man by my wyll whan the people had ſlayne my chyldren my kyn my frendes &amp; robbed &amp; ſpoyled my ſelfe certaynly I wolde haue ben a wroke right fayne and I had had power to my wyll but though my power were lytell certaynly I haue ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted them and wylled them to haue ben done to as they haue done to me / and wel I wote that is not the ordre of charyte But now I hertely crye god mercy our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed lady &amp; you holy charyte of the that myn enemyes here afore god oure bleſſed lady &amp; you thre I forgyue them all that they haue done agaynſt me / &amp; wyl not be auenged though I myght. And I pray you holy cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryte thoughe it were longe or I were aqueynted with you be not the lother to doo for me I ſore repente me that I haue thus vnreſonably &amp; vnwyttyngely abſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me frome you &amp; hertely I crye you mercy / &amp; praye
<pb facs="tcp:23368:8"/> you of your charyte to put out of your mynde my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous foly for certaynly I ſhall neuer doo ſo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re agayne but in euery thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge that I haue to do I ſhal deſyre your fauoure ſocour and your counſeyll and I vtterly denye and deſyre vengeaunce and neuer to dele with hym no more how ſomeuer I be done to but take it in pacyence and thynke as me ought of ryght that worſe than I haue ben doone to I haue deſerued to be done to / but that is not the worlde / for hym haue I ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued and pleaſed and dyſpleaſed almyghty god that is maker of all thynge and his holy begoten ſone that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued was of the holy gooſt and borne was of a pure chaſte vyrgyn and dyed for our redempcyon whan I haue greuouſly offended and broken his commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes in all thynge knowynge that I dyde not well wherfore my peryll is the more. Nor I haue not called after y<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bleſſed holy gooſt graces mercy ſocour and her helpe whan I haue ben in places of peryll of deedly ſynne. Nor I haue not called vpon that mooſt holy pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re chaſte and mooſt excellent vyrgyn and I haue be ſou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ght her of grace and ſhe tourned her vyſage frome me not for lacke of fayth but for me thoughe that her mooſt excellent charyte and chaſtyte muſte of very ryght ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre my ſynnes and all thynge that I pleaſed the worl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de with I knowe well that I dyſpleaſed hym that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demed me with his precyous paſſyon. And this I wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te well deſerueth a grete punyſſhemente than I haue it ſuffred and there as me lacked ſuffycyaunce and bol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>denes to come in the preſence of theym that I haue ſo greuouſly offended / wyll it pleaſe your goodnes Fay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>the Hope and Charyte charytable to goo and ſtere and be meane for me to the mother of mercy and pyte
<pb facs="tcp:23368:8"/> that ſhe wolde go for me to the gloryous trynyte and take you thre with her / for wele I wote the gloryous trynyte wyll nothynge denye that ſhe deſyreth they vnderſtande her perfyte charyte ſuche that euery crea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture that calleth after grace ſhe hath pyte vpon them haue they neuer ſo greuouſly offended. I ſholde fal in dyſpayre &amp; I had not perfyte truſt in her grace mercy &amp; pyte. And ſo I haue grete cauſe for to haue brought my Ioly ſoule in to grete bondage and in ſuche aduer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyte without remedy that it paſſeth my power to eaſe hym or helpe hym nor the grete ſpecyall truſte that I haue in that mooſt blyſſed good lady and in you holy Fayth Hope and Charyte.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶How the ſorowfull ſowle complayneth hym to the dyenge creature ſaynge thus.</head>
               <p>HOw nyghe haſte thou done with thy mayſter the worlde / how nyghe be ye twayne departed vnderſtandeſt thou not how vnſure he is / and at thy mooſt nede wyll fayle the / haſte thou not ſyth afore thys tyme in the tymes of thy grete aduerſytees and troubles / what hath he eaſed or proufyted the. Certay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne but lytell or nough / for and he haue flatered or dyſſymuled with the one daye or one houre he hathe lowred and grutched with the more than an hole yere therfore. Haſte thou not vnderſtande hym afore in all this tyme / but hanged vppon hym all ways as longe as thou myghteſt / and yet more lenger woldeſte thou yf that thou mighteſt / but now the ſeaſon and tyme is come that he wyll departe and go frome the / and what
<pb facs="tcp:23368:9"/> dyſtreſſe that euer thou arte in lytell wyl he fauour ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour or helpe the / ſuche as thou thynkeſt be thy fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des wyll ſhewe the a fayned fauoure tyll they knowe the certayne of thy ryches and yf thou haue good they wyll cheryſſhe and fauour the for the ſeaſon / and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playne and wayle thy deth. And yet they wolde full fayne thou were ago &amp; be ryght gladde with thy deth and whan tyme thyne eyen be cloſed / thy herynge ago thy ſpeche withdrawen &amp; may not ſpeke / than ſhalte thou ſe what thy mayſter the worlde wyll doo for the / ſeke thy cofers he wyll &amp; euery corner by the waye of lykelyhode that ony good is in / and lytell wyl they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parte with to the than / &amp; lytell compaſſyon wyll they haue vpon thy poore ſoule / and they fynde lytell or nought in thy cofers what wyll they ſaye / thou thou than they wyll ſaye thou were a fole a waſter thou cou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deſt not kepe / thou ſpendeſt more than thou haddeſt / thus wyll they ſaye by the / &amp; though they fynde moche thou ſhalt haue but lytell therof &amp; fare but lytell the better / and yf they fynde but lytell they wyll grudge with the &amp; ſaye the neuer a good worde / thynke theron by tymes &amp; be thyne owne frende / for and thou can not loue thy ſelfe who wyll loue the / canſte thou loue ony creature better than thy ſelfe / &amp; yf thou do ſoo in fayth thou arte not wyſe / remembre what I ſaye now / for thou ſhalte fynde this true euery worde / and thoughe I ſpeke thus greuouſly &amp; ſtraytly vnto the meruayll not for it. I am that ſhall abyde ſuffre and endure the paynes for thy defences. Alas that euer I was cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled with the / &amp; ſo haue I cauſe to ſaye / for I ſhall be punyſſhed without fauoure for thy dedes / how haſtely how ſoone I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not ſaye. ¶How vnauyſedly and how
<pb facs="tcp:23368:9"/> vnredyly thou purueyeſt for me I wote neuer how ſholde ony other creature haue compaſſyon vpon me whan thou haſte not that ſyght that thou were fyrſte fourmed a creature I haue alwayes be with the and neuer frome the and in the aege of thyne Inndcencye was kepe full vertuouſly to my grete comforte. And in thy myddle age was kepte full vycyouſly and ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to my grete ſorowe / and in thyne olde age lytell or noughte remembred thy wretchede lyuynge. Alas Alas Alas that euer thou &amp; I were coupled to gyther for the ſeaſon haſteth faſte that I muſt goo to paynes for thy myſrewle and endure payne whether it be eter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nall or for a longe ſeaſon I wote not what remedy thy worldely frendes wyll fynde to eaſe me. I am in grete drede I trowe they wyl haue but lytell compaſſyon on me that am thy poore ſoule / but giue there attendaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce for to berye the rychely and worſhypfully and make thy houſes clenly and to make thy purſe emptye and lytel compaſſyon or remembraunce wyl they haue vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the and me certaynely but lette me brenne eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly but yf the mercyes of hym that is almyghty by the meanes of his mooſt holy mother that pure chaſt may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den that helpeth euery ſynner that calleth after grace when there is none other remedy. Nowe farwell body thou ſhalt to erthe and lye and rotte and wormes ſhall ete the and I ſhall to paynes longe or elles eternally mercy bleſſyd lady that bare cryſte Iheſu our redemp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tour for in none other helpe I aſſure me.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶The lamentable lamentacyon of the dyenge body to the ſoule.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:23368:10"/>
               <p>ALas ſely ſoule the tourmentes and the paynes of mynne offences ſhall ye ſuffre I am ſoo ſory there can no tonge tell the ſorowe that I endure that haue brought you in ſuche bondage peryll daunger &amp; hduerſyte without remedy nor the hyghe and myghty mercyes of almyghty god whoſe mercyes can not be had but by the menes of his bleſſyd holy mother and yf ſhe that is ſoo chaſte ſo pure and ſoo holy wolde abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myne the abhomynacyon of oure ſynnes what ſhall I doo. I haue deſyred faythe hope &amp; charyte to be my ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uocates to her that bare oure lorde Iheſu cryſte. And whan I am anſwered agayne ſuche anſwere as I ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue I ſhall lette you wete.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶How the dyenge creature complayned hym to fayth hope and charyte ſaynge thus.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Ye holy fayth hope &amp; charyte where haue ye ben ſoo longe I haue lyued in grete drede how haue ye ſpedde haue ye bene with the quene of heuen lady of the worlde and empreſſe of hell that mooſte gloryous pure and chaſte vyrgyn that bare the ſone of god that ſholde redeme all mankynde / how wyll her chaſtyte her pure vyrgynyte receyue me that am a ſynner and ſuffre me to come to her preſence and putte a ſupplyca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon to her mooſte gloryous hygh and excellent pryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce that I haue ſo greuouſly offended her bleſſyd ſone &amp; her / wyll ſhe not abhorre ne dyſdayne too looke on me that am of al ſynners the moſte horryble and abhomy mooſte haboundant grace fynde a meane howe to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke a ſyght / but I haue herde ſaye of olde antyqueyte
<pb facs="tcp:23368:10"/> that ſhe is ſoo mercyable and ſo gracyous ſo ſynners whan they call after grace and haue holpen ſoo many ſynners that of ryght muſt haue peryſſhed ne her gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce had be. But what comforte ye haue of her mooſt ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>boundaunt grace I praye you lette me were / for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynly I lyue in grete dyſpayre / for here hath be with me ſythen that ye wente my ſoule &amp; complayned that he muſte peryſſhe eternally in my defaute and cryeth and wayleth the tyme that euer he was coupled with ſuche an vngracyous body that ſoo hath rewled hym / &amp; I can not gyue hym no comforte without you thre.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶The anſwere of fayth hope and charyte to the dyenge creature.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>E ſemeth fayth hope &amp; charyte haue done your meſſage and fonde that prynces ful gracyouſly dyſpoſed and ſayth that ſhe remembreth well how y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gloryous tryny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te choſe of one aſſente to be medyatryx &amp; meane bytwene god and man and that her grete wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppe and Ioye was cauſed for oure redempcyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che ſhe can not putte in oblyuyon / and alſo the grete ſorowes not one but many that ſhe had atte her ſones paſſyon and ſawe her bleſſyd and beſte beloued chylde dye ſoo tourmentouſly for the redempcyon of ſynners and he gylteles hym ſelfe in euery thynge but of his grete and mooſt ample grace mercy and charyte that he ſhewed vnto all ſynners and ſoo precyous ſo glory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſoo tender was neuer man as he was for he was the veray pure / and godhede medled with her pure caſte vyrgynyte and maydenhode and in her
<pb facs="tcp:23368:11"/> precyous body made his holy habytacyon nyne mone<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thes and in her ſoule eternally. And whan ſhe vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtode the prophecy of her grete mekenes deſyred that ſhe myghte be one of thoſe and ſympleſt ſeruaunt to her that ſholde bere the ſone of god and hym that ſhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de redeme all mankynde &amp; her grete mekenes thought her ſelfe not worthy to that mooſt holy occupacyon.</p>
               <p>And therfore be of good chere for we fayth hope and charyte wyll brynge you there and not leue you tyll ye be anſwered and ſyth ye haue put your ſpecyal truſt in vs to be your aduocates and layde aparte all temporal and wordely truſte we thre wyl not fayle you / and ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore putte your ſoule in comforte / and arme you with the armure of a ſure and a hole confeſſyon with a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull contrycyon purpoſynge to doo very ſatyſfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon and out of doubte / we hope ye ſhall ſpede ryght wel yf it be in your herte as ye ſpeke with your mouth and elles truſt not to our frendſhyp in no wyſe but go and labour your ſupplycacyon as effectually as ye can deuyſe and be out of all dyſpayre for we faythe hope &amp; charyte wyll not leue you for the truſte that ye haue al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wayes had in vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶How the dyenge creature calleth after the ſoule agayne.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here be ye dere ſoule that was with me but late complaynynge that ye muſte to payne for a longe whyle or elles eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and in my defaute and withoute reme<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy I haue ben in ſuche drede ſorowe tro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble and fere for you that no thynge coude comforte me
<pb facs="tcp:23368:11"/> tyll Fayth and Hope came to me and aſked me yf that I were not acqueynted with Charyte. And I haue an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwered them ſemely that I was neuer acqueynted ne conuerſaunt with hym &amp; that me repenceth ſore / now Fayth and hope haue brought me with hym and I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue humbly and lowly ſubmytted me to hym and lowly cryed hym mercy of my preſumpcyous foly promy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge that I wyll neuer offende hym more denyenge all ſuche as be his enemyes and as he loueth not venge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aunce / hatered / and cruelte and promyſed hym fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully that I wyl neuer dele with them more and I hope he hath pardoned me / and hath be in the company of Faith and hope to the moder of mercy for me &amp; brought me a ryght gracyous anſwere agayne. That ſhe can not put in oblyuyon the grete Ioye worſhyp and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte that ſhe had of the ſone of god for the redempcyon of vs ſynners / nor the maydenly and moderly compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon that ſhe ſuffred for hym in the tymes of his mooſt precyous paynefull and bytter paſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and that I ſhall haue hardines to come to the preſence of that mooſt roy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>all and emperyall prynces and put a ſupplycacyon to her / and therfore be of good chere and ſuffre your pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes pacyently for thoughe it be longe I hope it ſhall not be eternally and good dere ſoule whyle ye and I be togyder or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we departe puruey in youre wyſdome ſome remedy what ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be do to your eaſe and I wyl be ryghte agreable therto / for whan we twayne ones be deuyded and departed fewe or none wolde haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſyon in your payne. Se ye not how the worlde low<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth vpon vs now euery daye and is redy to departe frome vs euery daye for lytell thynge or nought &amp; leſſe wolde they doo for vs and we twayne were departed
<pb facs="tcp:23368:12"/> Therfore dere ſoule the remedyes that may be founde thorughe your wyſdome I praye you fynde them and I ſhall be ryght fayne to execute theym / for I am at this houre as ſory as is poſſyble ony wretche to be that I haue brought you in the peryll of daunger that ye be in and as fayne wolde be to doo that ſholde eaſe you and gladder than euer I was to do ony thynge that hath hurte you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶How the dyenge creature putteth his ſupply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacyon to the moder of mercy Mary replete with grace prynces of reuth / mercy &amp; pyte to whome all ſynners reſorteth whan they be ſocourles.</head>
               <p>MEkely beſecheth and ſorowfully complayneth your dredefull ſupplyaunt that all my longe lyf vnto my eldeſt age haue lyued and not obeyed the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundementes of almyghty god in noo thynge but myſueſd my lyfe in all the ſeuen deedly ſynnes / and ſynfully and ſymply haue occupyed my fyue wyttes and ſette aſyde all vertues and vſed and occupyed all vyces and ſerued the deuyll the worlde and the fleſſhe hauynge very knowlege bothe of good and euyll and knowe wel that that peaſed them deſpyſed dyſpleaſed almyghty god. I ſpared not to dyſpleaſe god but I dredde to dyſpleaſe them and now hath a ſergeaunt of armes be with me and layde vpon me the mace of his offyce cruelly and hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded me to make me re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy euery houre for I ſhall not wete whan I ſhal be cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led to my Iugement y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> certayne of deth he hath brou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght me in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greuous infyrmyte that none erthly me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dycyne can cure me myn enemyes be ſo grete in multy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tude
<pb facs="tcp:23368:12"/> and haue ouercome me &amp; al my defautes brought with them. And I wote well they wyll accuſe me my worldy frendes hath for ſake me I haue cryed and cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led after them to anſwere for me and they haue anſwe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red me ryght ſtraytly and vnfrendly that they neyther dare ne can ne wyl not anſwere for me nor excuſe me And ſhortly they be departed away from my good aun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gell fyrſte reaſon drede and conſcyence and my fyue wyttes haſteth them faſte from me warde and leueth me deſtytute and all one / and where to haue ſocour ne helpe I wote not but as it fortuneth me in good tyme may I ſaye I mette me with Fayth Hope and Charyte and they haue promiſed me that they wyl ſpeke to your mooſt excellent benygne grace and mercy for me and ſo I truſte they haue / for certayne of your mooſt pure chaſte vyrginyte and vnwemmed maydenhode I was neuer in thought. And I haue hoped &amp; truſted to your mercyes alwaye I haue herde ſaye that ye be mother of orphans and I wys I am a very orphan fatherles and motherles / ne be dyſſolat comforte and ſocour to all tho that be deſtytute dyſſolate and ſoceurles I wys lady that am I. for I haue neyther ſocoure helpe nor conforte of no creature but onely the truſte that I haue in your benygne grace ye be guyde vnto them that be out of the waye and ſeke the meanes for to come in to the ryght waye. A blyſſed lady I haue be ſoo longe out of the waye that I fere and drede for too call to you for grace / but as Faythe Hope and Charyte haue put me in comforte how lothe ye be to ſe your bleſſyd ſones precyous and bytter paſſyon loſte in my creature and they haue gyuen me hardynes for to call vpon your mooſt noble and benygne grace. And ſoo good bleſſed
<pb facs="tcp:23368:13"/> lady with humble dredfull &amp; ſorowful herte &amp; mynde I beſeche your mooſt benygne grace mercy and pyte to ſet me in the tyght way of ſaluacyon and make me one of the partyners of your blyſſed ſones precyous paſſyon &amp; of your maydenly &amp; motherly compaſſyons &amp; as ye became borowe for Mary Egyptyan to your blyſſed ſone. So good lady be my borowe that I ſhall neuer from hens forth wylfully offende your blyſſed ſone nor you but ſore repente that euer I ſawe / herde or dyde ony thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges that hath dyſpleaſed your bleſſed ſone or you beynge in wyll neuer to retourne to ſynne and wretchednes agayne but rather to dye than wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to do ony thynge that ſholde dyſpleaſe my lorde cryſt Iheſu or you. Now prynces excellent &amp; excelly<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of myght &amp; worthynes al creatures as in dygnyte my herte lady my wordely chefe goodes pray your ſone to haue mercy vpon me ſyth in all my greteſt myſchefe to your grace I flee I can no ferder refute to fynde ony conſolacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; ſyth my hope and truſte is onnely ſet in you be ye my refuge now in this grete trybulacyon co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer my ſynfull ſoule with the mantyll of your mercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es and ſet your ſones precyous paſſyon betwene me &amp; eternall dampnacyon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶The ſupplycacyon of our lady to our lorde Iheſu her ſone for the ſeke creature.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Iheſu my lorde my god mooſt bleſſed ſone in whome is all plente of grace &amp; of vnthoughted mercy to &amp; for all ſynners that in ſtedfaſt fayth and aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſured hope deuoutly call vnto you for helpe and grace &amp; hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly beſechynge mercy &amp; forgyuenes of theyr myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſawtes
<pb facs="tcp:23368:13"/> and offences to you I come as a ſolyciter and a beſecher for this ſeke creature whiche with humble and ſorowfull and a contryte herte ſueth contynually for your grace and pardon that it myght lyke you to in clyne you of your vnyte pyte to his requeſtes and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playntes and graciouſly to conſyder his nedes and cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes he is ſore abaſſhed and dyſcomfyted in hym ſelfe &amp; as who ſayth vtterly confounded conſyderynge his greuous &amp; depe ſynnes by the whiche he hath prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked your wrath and indygnacyon by the whiche alſo he is ſore encombred and ſtandeth in grete daungere of his enemy &amp; namely he fereth hym of your dredfull Iugement for well he woteth yf ye do hym Iuſtyce he is but loſte foreuer / yet for all this he dyſpayreth not of your mercy for he is in good opynyon and truſteth to reioyſe your pardone and to be reconſyled to grace whereupon he ſueth contynually vnto you as he may and dare / for he knoweth hym ſelfe ſo depely charged in ſynne and ſoo ferre elonged from grace by ſynne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he thynketh hym ſelfe vnworthy to approche to offre his owne prayer / therfore he ſueth by meanes and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyally by me to whome he calleth inportunely with py<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teous &amp; waylynge voyce &amp; ſeketh not but contynueth in ſobbynge &amp; wepynge ſoo lamentably that my herte erneth to here / and certes I can not me no lenger con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne but to inſtant his prayers and to put me in your grace for hym for he calleth me the mother of mercye for encheſon that I bare you whiche be the very fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes and welles of mercy and haue it of vnſeuerall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prete to be mercyable to all ſynners / &amp; for this he cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lengeth me in maner as though I ſholde owe of dute to enterparte my labours and prayers in this behalfe
<pb facs="tcp:23368:14"/> with hym and for hym / and to ſue for the haſty ſpede of his reconſylacyon and that he letteth not to put me in mynde that I was ordeyned of god to be meane by<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>twene hym and man / &amp; certes I alowe wel his mynde therin / for true it is that I ought ſoo to be that lyke wyſe that ye my dere lorde and ſone deſcended frome heuen to erth by me and become partyner of mannes nature by me. Soo all ſynners that be not in eſtate of grace ſholde be reconſyled and reſtored to grace by me and be made partyners of your Ioye by me. ¶This is well ſygnyfyed in the fygure of aarons rode whiche bare a floure myraculouſly as ſcrypture wytneſſeth. The whiche rode ſygnyfyeth me lyke as the floure be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tokeneth you / for as a rode groweth dyrectly vpwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de and is the ſtreyght meane bytwene y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rode and the floure / and he that wyll clyne together the floure muſt aſſende by the rode or elles bowe the rode &amp; cauſe the flowre to ſtoupe / ſo he that wylleth to ryſe from ſynne muſt ryſe by me / and he that wyll acclyne your grace and reioyſe your pardon muſt bow me by prayer that I may cauſe you to ſtoupe that is to ſaye too inclyne to here prayer and requeſtes and to let dyſcende your bemes of grace to them. ¶Lo thus my dere ſone and lorde it is open and euydente that I am ordeyned to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>conſyle man and that / it is in manere my dewte and offyce ſo to doo / wherfore ſyth this ſeke creature thus contynually and vnfatygably cryeth to me with pyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and dolefull complaynte and requyreth me ſoo ſtraytly that I can not ſeas to put me in endure for hym and enterparte my labours with hym for hym / and certes it is not onely for his inportune ſuyte and prayer but alſo for other conſyderacyons reſonable &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:23368:14"/> charytable that moueth me to tender &amp; inſtant his cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes / one is that he is alyed to me ryght nye bi ſpyrytual cognacyon for bothe we haue one fader that is god whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che is your fader by creacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and one moder the chyrche whiche is our moder by regeneracyon thus is he my bro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der &amp; I his ſyſter and now my lorde me ſemeth ryght vnſyttynge me beynge a quene to ſe my brother a pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner I at lyberte and he in thraldome. I in blyſſe and he in tourment / wherfore I am conſtrayned as who ſayth by nature to ſue for his delyuerynge and reconſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge and this is one of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyderacyons that reſona<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bly moueth me to ſue for his pardon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶The ſeconde conſyderacyon.</head>
               <p>ANother is that ſyth it lyked you of your grete bounte and ineſtymable charyte for the reconſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lynge of man to take of me your handmayden fleſſhe &amp; blode and bone and the ſayd fleſſhe and bloode to offre in ſacrefyce for redempcyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of me and this and all other whom it hath and ſhal lyke you to call to your fayth me ſemeth I ought not / for as moche as in me lyeth to ſee that thynge myſcarye whiche you haue ſoo precyouſly redemed and bought as derely as ye bought me &amp; with the ſame fleſſhe and blode that ye toke of me your hum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble creature and handmayden.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶The thyrde conſyderacyon.</head>
               <p>ANother is this I and euery your other creatu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res before youre partye bowed to ſue meanes to honoure to worſhyppe to gloryfye you in that we
<pb facs="tcp:23368:15"/> can or may / but ſo it is that in Iuſtyfyenge of this ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner grete honoure and glory ſhall be to you and to your ſayntes for your ſcrypture ſayth. Gaudium eſt angelis dei ſuper vno peccatore penitentiam agenti. That is to ſaye Ioye and gladnes is to your aungelles the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſyon of one ſynner contryte and penytent and in an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>other place your ſcrypture ſayth. Magis gaudium eſt ſuper peccatore penitentiam agenti quam ſuper nona<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ginta nouen iuſtis. ¶That is to ſaye and to ſygnyfye that more Ioye and honour is to god in reconſylynge a ſynner that is in full and aſſured purpoſe to perſeuer in grace than in grete multytude of other ryghtwys that neuer offended. ¶Wherfore my lorde as I am bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>unde to honour and gloryfy you ſo am I bounde in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to make inſtaunce for reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſylynge of this your crea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture in the whiche thynge ye ſhall be gretely honoured and gloryfyed and theſe be the thynges that moueth me to inſtaunce and ſolycyte his cauſes and to ſubmyt me for hym.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶The fourth conſyderacyon</head>
               <p>FOrthermore I ſe in hym grete abylyte and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kelyhode to ſe that creature that may ſerue you honoure and gloryfye you for he entyerly dyſpleaſed with hym ſelfe that he hath ſo greuouſly ſynned and offended your grace and he is ryght heuy and contryte therfore and he remembreth hym many ſythes of his olde ſynnes not as delytynge ne hauynge pleaſure in theym but to his ſhame and grete remors and he hath theym in perfyte hatred in ſo moche that he wolde not offende agayne in the leeſt of theym for all the worlde
<pb facs="tcp:23368:15"/> he hathe faſtened his entente and pourpoſe to be here after all of other demeanynge thrugh your helpe and grace and he wyll gladly do penaunce for that he hath treſpaſſed and he lowly ſubmytteth hym ſelfe to the correcyon of youre chyrche and wylfully aſſenteth to paye the fynaunce and ſuffre the penaunce attaxed by your chyrche and to do ſatyſfaccyon as is for his freyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te poſſyble. And where as he ſayth hym ſelfe not of aby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyte ne power to do ſatyſfaccyon as hym oweth in that behalfe he putteth hym ſelfe holy in your grace and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytteth hym to your grete mercy and to the meryte of your paſſyon whiche counteruayleth and preuayleth all the penaunce and ſatyſfaccyon that myght be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyble for to be done by all the worlde from Adam tyll to the laſte creature that ſhall be borne. ¶And he py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly cryeth to me and beſecheth me to enterpoſe my merytes betwene your Iugement and hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and to offre in ſacryfyce for hym the ſobbynge and ſyghynges the ſorowfull and lamentable terys that I wepte for you in your tender age and chyldhode whan Symeon pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phecyed to me your paſſyon / and whan I had loſt you in Iheruſalem and the ſorowes that I ſuffred for you in tyme of your paynefull and greuous paſſyon whan the ſwerde of ſorowe peryſſhed my herte. And certes I am ryght well content and gladde ſo to do. And I beſeche you ſoo to accepte my merytes for his / as he goodly deſyreth and to ſet my ſorowes and teres of py<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te in place of his penaunce and contrycyon. ¶Forther more it myght lyke you to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyder the grete labour and beſynes of Fayth Hope and Charyte and namely for charyte whiche ſueth for hym contynually and neuer is ydell but beſy to labour for hym / and ſhe cleueth and
<pb facs="tcp:23368:16"/> called for me for hym inceſſauntly to ſe the expeccyon of his cauſes / and ſhe vndertaketh for his aberinge and well ye wote that her deſyre &amp; prayer maye not be voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ne fruſtrate but ſhe muſt be gracyouſly herde in all her goodly requeſtes and deſyres. She hath alſo recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued fayth and hope on her partye for this ſeke creature and hath profeſſed to kepe your fayth inuyolably and hope hath put hym in ful aſſuraunce of your mercy / for thoughe it ſoo be that he ſe not in hym ſelfe wherof he may truſte to reioyſe your pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / yet ſhe ſheweth hym that in you is ſoo greate promptues of mercy and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynuall cuſtome that you be wonte and vſed alwaye to forgyue and haue of naturall proprete for to be mercy able to all ſynners that it maketh hym bolde to faſten the anker of his hope in you and truſteth fynally to ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke a vyage in the porte of your mercy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶The concluſyon of our ladyes ſupplycacyon.</head>
               <p>NOw my lorde ſyth all the good abylytes and dyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſico<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ns vnto grace be in this creature by your ſuffraunce / there is no more to doo but ſhat ye let deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cende your grace to the veſſell ſo dyſpoſed and that you voucheſaufe to ſuffre hym reioyſe your pardon and re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>conſyle hym to your chyrche and make hym a membre therof the ſoner and ſpedlyer for this my prayer and re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>queſt. I you beſeche my mooſt dere lorde and ſone who me it hathe lyked you al waye to here gracyouſly and neuer ſuffre to departe boteles of petycyon for whiche be to you and to your mooſt honourable and drad father with the holy gooſt your egall pere euerlaſlynge Ioyi honour and glory Amen.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:23368:16"/>
            <p>¶Her endeth a lytell treatyſe of the dyenge creature Enprynted at London in Fleteſtrete at the ſygne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſone by Wynkyn de Worde. Anno dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i. M.CCCCC.xiiii.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut representing a man in bed looking up toward Jesus Christ on the cross surrounded by people and animals, and with a devil or demon below the bed;</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:23368:17"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>bordered printer's device of a shield with the mark of Robert Copland, suspended from a tree and supported by a stag and a hind (McKerrow 36)</figDesc>
                  <q>¶Melius eſt nomen bonum <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>quam</ex>
                     </expan> diuitie multe. <bibl>Prou. xxii.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>ROBERT COPLAND</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:23368:17"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:23368:18"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:23368:18"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
